So I want to start today with a
question.
If you had one word to describe how you
feel when you watch the news,
what would it be? Please share it with
your neighbor.
So I will not even ask people to we will
not we will not even move the mic.
I can see the faces.
I suspect your answers have something to
do with angry,
uh tired,
frustrated,
discouraged, overwhelmed.
passport worried uh hopeless
indifferent
You know, and honestly, I don't blame
you. I don't blame you because
uh and this is not just for you here in
Kenya, but for many parts of the world,
we are living through
a moment. Uh if you
if you look at imagine what
I I I guarantee you the Iranians are
feeling the same way you're feeling. I
guarantee you the Ukrainians are
probably feeling worse than you're
feeling. Uh so but here in Kenya, let's
focus for here in Kenya.
Uh I know I the people in in in the Adam
Mchunu churches in in in those countries
will preach for their country.
So but for here in Kenya, the last few
weeks we have watched parents
who grieve children will never come
home.
Between January last year and March this
year, we've had 1,636
missing children who've not been found.
And 1,952
abductions, only 300 have been found
between that. You know your difference.
Schools around the country are
experiencing unrest. The last 2 weeks
the schools have been closed.
We've watched the cost of living
I think the music is continuing on that
side.
So, what's the cost of living continue
to squeeze households
that are already under pressure.
Fuel and food prices are increasing and
yet for many people
incomes have remained exactly the same.
And we've watched endless corruption
allegations, questions about
accountability that are not being
answered, questions about leadership,
audit reports that continue to raise a
concerns about irregular expenditure
that cannot be explained. Just this
year, this 6 months, we've had 27
billion being used on travel and
conferences and allowances while
government in continue
impose taxes, new taxes, levies, fees on
ordinary Kenyans who already struggling
to meet. And it is not surprising that
frustration is arising.
There is a
the the what is it called? Amnesty
has a freedom index report and they are
saying
that public demonstrations have more
than doubled in the last 2 years and
they are mainly because of economic
hardship and concerns about governance.
Now, increasingly many people are
feeling like life is becoming harder and
harder, not easier.
More taxes, more levies, more pressure,
less opportunity, less accountability,
less trust, less hope.
And perhaps what is concerning
is not that people are hungry. No,
hunger is understandable. What is
concerning many people is that people
are tired.
Tired of hoping, tired of waiting, tired
of being disappointed, tired of
believing things can change and tired of
caring.
Perhaps this leaves us with a with a
deeper question.
What do you do? What do you do as a
follower of Jesus when you're confronted
by the realities of your nation, your
city, and your generation? What do you
do?
Do you speak or stay silent? Do you
engage or do you withdraw? Do you lean
in or do you look away? What do you do?
And if that is you, you've been asking
yourself such questions, Karibu sana. Uh
because this month in Mavuno Church we
are we are starting a new brand a new a
brand new series.
It's a new brand. Anyway, after the
hashtag moving from outrage to action.
And over the next four weeks this is
what you're going to talk about and
we're going to explore as a follower of
Jesus
in an age where there are viral hashtags
and trending headlines and
in the world we live in.
Where injustice happens, you know, this
world that we live in injustice happens
today like this. Sindio?
What happens immediately? A hashtag
appears.
And then a crisis erupts because now
people are it is being exposed and then
a conversation begins. Sindio?
People pay attention. People react. They
either go to the streets, do something.
You know, people do something. They
speak up.
But often
often
before that injustice is addressed
the hashtag has disappeared.
Before that problem is solved
the world has
started speaking about something else
because a new injustice has happened and
new hashtag has appeared
new crisis is being exposed and so
people have gone there to address that
one and forgotten what they are
addressing. This This last month is a
good example. Osebola
uh
burning Utumishi oh like
>> like
And the heart of this is the heart of
this series. What happens when the
hashtag hits? How do we move from
from from
beyond awareness to meaningful action?
And so today
we will talk about a man
uh who finds himself in a similar
situation in the Bible.
And this man is called Nehemiah. Let me
give you a bit of context. So, the story
starts um
in one of the darkest season of the of
of Israel.
Because
Jerusalem has been invaded.
The temple has been destroyed.
Uh many of God's people have been taken
into exile. In fact, they took everyone
who was anything. Any smart person, any
priest, any leader, any lord, any
everyone. Everyone who would have had an
impact in that society was taken away.
Any educated person was taken away. The
people who are left were the sick and
the and the and the poor.
And so the city is broken. Years later
some of them have returned home, but the
city is still broken. It is still
in ruins. The wall is in ruins. The
grounds are still burned. The people are
living in vulnerability and disgrace.
And now
Nehemiah is not in Jerusalem.
He's in a place called Susa, a city
called
which was the capital of then the king
of the Medes and the Persians. And he is
he's serving in the palace as a
cupbearer to the king.
And Nehemiah chapter 1 verse 1 to 9. I
don't want us to read read it together.
So, 1 2 go. The words of Nehemiah, son
of Hacaliah, in the month of Kislev, in
the 20th year, while I was still in the
citadel of Susa, Hanani, one of my
brothers, came from Judah with some
other men, and I questioned them about
the Jewish remnant that had survived the
exile, and also about Jerusalem. They
said to me, "Those who survived the
exile are back in the province and are
in great trouble and disgrace. The wall
of Jerusalem is broken down and its
gates its gates have been burned with
fire."
When I heard these things, I sat down
and wept. For some days I mourned and
fasted and prayed before the God of
heaven. Then I said, "Lord, the God of
heaven, the great and awesome God, who
keeps his covenant of love with those
who love him and keep his commandments,
let your ear be attentive and your eyes
open to hear the prayer of your
your servant is praying before you day
and night for your servants, the people
of Israel. I confess the sins we
Israelites, including myself and my
father's family, have committed against
you.
We have acted very wickedly towards you.
We have not obeyed the commands and
decrees and laws you gave your servant
Moses. Remember the instruction you gave
your servant Moses saying, 'If you are
unfaithful, I will scatter you among the
nations. If you But if you return to me
and obey my commands, then, even in your
if your exile people are at the farthest
horizon, I will gather them from there
and bring them to the place I have
chosen as my dwelling place for my
name.' I was cupbearer to the king. Oh,
come on.
Anyway,
Nehemiah receives a report that is
alarming. The wall of Jerusalem is
broken down and its gates have been
burned with fire.
And today that may sound dramatic, like
just a wall.
But in the ancient world, the wall was
never just a wall. Remember Jericho,
there's even the wall was even big
enough for somebody to live in.
You know, the the wall represented
security. It represented stability. It
represented dignity. Uh without walls,
enemies could cut will.
Trade suffered.
Economic activity slowed down. Families
lived in fear.
The situation The city's reputation
deteriorated. Every broken stone was a
daily reminder that things were not as
they should be.
And if if Imagine if Jerusalem had
social media.
What would the hashtags be?
Anyone? What would the hashtags be?
Wall broken down.
Save Jerusalem. Burn the gates or burnt
gate, sorry. Burnt gate, something like
that. But yes, that that's how it would
be.
Meanwhile,
uh as he received the alarming report,
Nehemiah is hundreds, thousands of
kilometers away.
And he's living his best life.
Nehemiah is not living among the ruins.
He's not standing in the beside the
broken walls. He's not struggling to
survive. He is living in the palace. He
is serves as cupbearer to the king. This
is You know, cupbearer to the king is
the one who would just in case the king
was going to be poisoned, so they would
sip the poison. If they don't fall, they
give to the king.
But they were next to the king. They
they they were probably like the king's
PA in normal day. Call it something
close to that. Uh and so, what does that
mean? Probably akuna SUV, akuna red
lights up. Probably akuna Kacheska.
Probably akuna good bucks, travel, the
works. Hizo zote. That was Nehemiah.
Every day he was walking in the halls of
power. This is a kingdom that had
conquered most of civilization and the
king you are serving the king directly.
So, he was walking in the halls of
power.
Every day he enjoyed influence. He
enjoyed security. He enjoyed privilege.
The crisis was real, true. Yes, it was
real. It's happening somewhere else far
away from him.
If anyone had the luxury of just
crawling past the problem,
it was Nehemiah.
If anyone had the luxury of being
detached, shaking his head and moving on
with life,
it was Nehemiah.
If anyone could have said, "Not my
circus, not my monkey." it was Nehemiah.
And this is how often we experience the
broken brokenness of the world.
A news alert, a social media post, a
hashtag,
a WhatsApp message, a headline. We see
it. We react to it. We feel bad. We talk
to our friends about it. We social
network on social media and then that's
it. We move on.
Cuz it does not affect us as directly as
as it is affecting those people.
But Nehemiah does not move on. The Bible
says, "When I heard these things, I sat
down and wept." Nehemiah does not
dismiss the report. He does not. He He
doesn't complain about the system. He
doesn't scroll to the next story. He
sits. He grieves. He moans. He fasts and
he prays. You know, when it comes to
engaging with brokenness and injustices
around us, people have differing
opinions about the place of prayer.
Some believe prayer is unnecessary.
Siyo?
We And And they believe we don't need
prayer. We need action.
Others believe that prayer alone is
sufficient. Just pray, you're good to
go.
And they spend years in prayer closets,
in prayer mountains,
but they never step into the thing
they're praying into, they're praying
for, or praying about.
Nehemiah believed neither.
He He understood that prayer
is not a substitute for action.
Prayer is
is a prayer
and also action is not a substitute for
prayer.
And so as we witness all of
is happening in our country, now bring
it to us.
And our world today, it's very easy to
get overwhelmed.
The problems we face are large, they are
complex, they are big, they are
overwhelming.
And even before you begin to concede
figure out one problem, the extent to
which this is a problem, and one has
come up. And before you get to
understand this one, another coming up.
And we feel powerless. We and they and
and and we easy for us to often drift
towards any of these two extremes.
Extreme number one, and we it's silence.
Silence.
The end is silence. At the temptation to
disengage, to look away, to convince
ourselves that somebody else will deal
with
Silence says it is not my concern.
Silence says it retreats into a private
life. It focuses on personal success,
personal comfort,
uh personal uh
Silence avoids difficult conversations.
Silence convinces itself that staying
uninvolved
is the same thing as staying neutral.
But reality is neutrality is rarely
neutral.
When good people say nothing, broken
systems rem- often remain unchallenged.
And many believers don't even vote. Why?
What's the use?
But when we remain silent,
broken systems often remain
unchallenged.
The people believe that they
they need to enforce their system. They
wake up early in the morning and vote.
The believers who are able to who have
hung out with God a bit and are able to
see this is wrong,
they don't challenge it.
Edmund Burke says, "The only necessary
the the only thing necessary for for for
the triumph of evil is for good men to
do nothing."
There's a story about a pastor in
in in in a Catholic pastor in
in
in Poland. When when when when when
Hitler was was moving across Europe and
conquering.
And he said, "When they first came for
the for the Protestants, I did not
complain. When they first came for the
Presbyterians, I did not complain
because that was that's not us. Then
they came
for the Protestants.
We did not complain because it was not
us. Then I think he mentioned a pole
a news reporter or something like that.
And then finally they came for us.
But there was no one to speak for us."
So the more as we keep quiet, what we
consider neutrality is not neutrality.
In fact, we are enabling evil.
The other end The other end is outrage.
The other The other extreme we fall into
is outrage.
Endless frustration. Endless criticism.
Endless commentary.
Outrage is always angry. Always
reacting. Always pointing fingers. It
knows exactly who it is to blame, it
generates heat but rarely
gives direction or light.
It can tell you everything that is
wrong, who is wrong, but it struggles to
build what is right.
Over time, outrage becomes exhausting.
It consumes our attention, it steals our
peace,
and it leaves us cynical about any
positive change.
What makes Nehemiah remarkable is
he chooses neither of those things. He
choose He refuses to sit in the
indifference.
He also
chooses to to
He refuses again the paralysis of
consistent continuous outrage.
He chooses a third way, which is what I
want us to focus
on today. He brings the burden first
before God in prayer.
He allows the brokenness
around him, of the news he has gotten,
to burden his heart. He doesn't just
like move on. He uh he sits in that
pain.
He takes the responsibility for the
peace of the world that God has placed
in front of him.
And that is what exactly happens in
chapter 2.
So, between chapter 1 and chapter 2,
where he hears his chapter 1 he hears
the story and starts praying and
fasting. Between chapter 1 and chapter 2
is 4 months.
4 months
of praying, 4 months of fasting, 4
months of carrying the burden of
Jerusalem to God. Then the opportunity
presents itself. The king notices
something is wrong, and the burden is
that began in Nehemiah's heart finds an
expression.
And I want us to read it.
Chapter 2,
verse 1 to 5, and then verse 17.
So, in the month of We go together. Want
to go? In the month of Nisan, in the
20th year of King Artaxerxes,
when the wine was brought for him, I
took the wine and gave it to the king. I
had not been sad in his presence before.
So, the king asked me, "Why does your
face look sad when you're not ill? This
can only This can be nothing but sadness
for of heart."
I was very much afraid.
But, I said to the king, "May the king
live forever. Why should my face not
look sad when the city where my
ancestors are buried lies in ruins and
its gates have been destroyed by fire?"
The king said to me, "What is it you
want?" Then, I prayed to the God of
heaven, and I answered to the king,
"If it pleases the king and if your
servant has found favor in his sight,
let him send me to the city of Judah
where my ancestors are buried so that I
can rebuild it." Now,
the king accepts, sends him, and verse
17,
"Then, I said to them, 'You see the
trouble we are in. Jerusalem lies in
ruins and its gates have been burned
with fire. Come, let us rebuild the wall
of Jerusalem and we will no longer be in
disgrace.' I also told them about the
gracious hand of God of my God on me and
what the king had said to me. They
replied, 'Let us start rebuilding.' So,
they began this good work."
See, Nehemiah refuses to remain a
spectator.
While others were aware of the problem,
Nehemiah took responsibility.
He understood
that awareness
will not rebuild the wall.
Conversation alone will not rebuild the
wall. Outrage alone will not rebuild the
wall.
He moves from burden to responsibility,
from concern to contribution. Nehemiah
says, "Let us rebuild." He moves from
talking about the problem to becoming
part of the solution. And my one point
of this message
is this, pick up a stone, don't throw
it, build a wall. Pick up a stone,
build a wall. Tell your neighbor, pick
up a stone
and build a wall.
And perhaps that is a challenge of many
of us today. We live in a world that
rewards commentary.
We know how to post. We know how to
paint something in the in the
appropriate light. We know how to
debate. We know how to criticize. We
know how to identify what is wrong. We
know it. But eventually, every burden
asks the same questions. Now that you
know, what are you going to do about it?
Now that you know, what are you going to
do about it? Now there are there are
three responses that we see from
Nehemiah which I want us to take on
today.
Uh
response number one is recognize the
wall. Recognize the wall.
Before Nehemiah could rebuild the wall
before Nehemiah could rebuild the wall
you know what he did?
He had to first recognize it.
He had to allow himself to see what
others
have learned to live
He one of the greatest dangers one of
the greatest dangers of our time is
apathy.
It's not opposition.
It is apathy.
Like just moving on.
And a good number of us especially a
good number of us are doing either in
businesses or are working in careers
that your employer is not here in Kenya.
And so the the taxes that what are not
really affecting you. And so you may
feel like
pole ni
eh
na kufil you're going by road. Pole ni
nzuri. But
but let me tell you, your time is
coming.
Your time is coming.
Your time is coming. And this is a time
for you to act before it comes for you.
Probably the reason the economy in the
country still standing is because of
some of you not have uh they they're not
really the
earning from the country.
You get?
Uh but don't think that that will
protect you.
Uh the there's a
Esther was told as Esther Esther was
like, "Oh, you know, when when Mordecai
was telling her, 'Oh, Israelites are
going to be killed.'" And he's like,
"Oh, you know, you know, the king
doesn't take anyone just like that. He's
not calling me for a whole month." And
what did Mordecai tell her?
"Do not think that you'll be protected
from this." But even if you don't
uh
the hand of God will
God will raise a savior from the
somewhere. I'm paraphrasing. You are an
Israelite and it will come to you as
well.
And that's the same thing that will
happen to us.
Don't think you not be affected by this.
You also a Kenyan. It will come to you
as well.
Sawa?
Anyway, where was I? Apathy. We are
exposed to much suffering, injustice,
news, uh
and bad news that
we it we become emotionally numb.
Another scandal, another the another
person such searching for justice,
another disappearance, and another
corruption case, another
of power. Over time, what once what once
what once shocked us
is no stops surprising us. What once
burdened us
uh no longer moves us. And
Jeremiah reminds us
that as followers of Jesus, we are
called to keep our hearts soft.
We are called to resist
the temptation of saying it is not my
problem. We are to resist the temptation
of hardening our hearts, see the plight
of others. We are called to resist
comfort from a distance.
We are called to recognize the
walls around us.
And and and and and and say and and name
them for what they are. So, is there a
wall of corruption? Is there a wall of
environmental degradation? Is there a
wall of
of voter apathy around you that you need
to recognize?
What wall, let me ask you, what wall
have you stopped seeing?
What brokenness have you learned to live
with?
What injustice no longer troubles you
the way it once did in our society?
Because before God
uses Nehemiah's hands,
you know what he first had to do? He had
to open Nehemiah's eyes.
And maybe that's the first step towards
rebuilding what is broken. Is asking God
to help us recognize the broken wall.
Asking God to help us recognize the
problem, like see it and not to be aloof
about it. The second wall The second
thing The second step is respond to the
wall, and that is pray.
Respond to the wall. Once Nehemiah
recognizes the wall, he responds to his
is to it. Not ignore it. He does not
explain it away. He takes it to God. And
one of the things that strikes me about
Nehemiah is that he refuses to separate
prayer from engagement. Before he ever
ever ever speaks to the king, he first
goes to pray.
Be Before even he ever travels to the to
Jerusalem, before he lays
a hand on a single stone, he brings the
burden first to God. And notice how
specific his prayers are. They are not
about general well-being of the world or
the people of that area. No, no, no, no,
no. Praying about a wall, a particular
wall, a particular burden, a particular
problem that God has placed in his
heart. The temple was also in ruins, but
you find it is God moved the heart of
Ezra
temple, not Nehemiah.
You know, God So, Nehemiah was praying
about the particular problem he had or
or or burden that God put in his heart.
I wonder, what is God burdening you
about today?
What is that issue that keeps stirring
something inside of you? What is that
injustice that bothers you and takes
away your sleep? What is that situation
that keeps making keeps making you say,
"This is not right."?
Perhaps it is corruption.
Probably it is poor governance. Probably
it is inequality. Uh probably it is
children's rights. Probably it is police
brutality. Po- probably it is poverty. I
know poverty is one for me.
Perhaps it is the way vulnerable people
are treated in society.
If it asks you, pray about it.
If it burdens you, pray about it. If it
breaks your heart, what do you do?
Pray about it.
If it If it makes you lose your sleep,
what do you do? Pray about it. Let me be
clear.
Prayer, though, is not a cop-out. It's
not a way an exit strategy. No. Prayer
is what Christians Prayer is not what
Christians do instead of acting. Prayer
is where faithful actions begin.
So,
prayer aligns our hearts to God's heart.
Prayer gives us wisdom. Prayer gives us
courage and discernment. Prayer keeps
our engagement from becoming
reactionary.
Prayer
keeps us from becoming cynical and
self-righteous. Nehemiah understood that
before he could rebuild the wall
around Jerusalem, God first needed to
build something in his inside him.
Identify your wall. So, this is what you
do. Identify your wall.
Name it. Make sure you name it. Don't
say it's something around No, no, no,
no. Name that burden and then bring it
before God. Pray over it intentionally.
Pray over it consistently. Pray over it
specifically. Pray over it because most
of the time the burden that God places
on your hearts are clues to the work he
may be calling you to do.
And to the influence he may be calling
you of.
But you have to first sit with it and
pray about it.
And then the third step is rebuild the
wall.
And that is the third challenge we
Nehemiah is giving us. Rebuild the wall.
At some point, Nehemiah gets up from
prayer
and picks up a stone and that is where
many of us get stuck. We care, we pray,
we discuss.
We post, we debate, we probably send out
pesa.
But eventually, someone has to build.
Someone has to do what? To build.
At some As we move towards another
election season, I know in Kenya
election starts immediately the election
ends. Election season starts Campaign
starts immediately the election ends.
But we are getting into some intense
election season.
And And as a as temptations the There
are great temptations facing us
to confuse com- commentary, people
giving their opinion
and contribution.
We will spend months listening to
politicians,
watching debates, sharing videos,
arguing in WhatsApp groups, and posting
our opinions.
We will know what is wrong with our
country.
We will know who is to blame. We will
know which policies we agree with and
which ones we we oppose. We will know
who is the best leader for this nation
and who is not. We will know even how
this this new leader can save the nation
and how they can kill the nation. We
know it.
But following the conversation is not
the same thing as changing the
conversation.
Nehemiah teaches us to be faithful. To
that faithful engagement requires more
attention. It requires participation as
well.
It is possible that everything that is
wrong with the nation
it is possible to know everything that
is wrong with the nation but still
contribute nothing
to its healing.
Which I think is what has been happening
to us.
In the last four years, I feel we have
really
known what is wrong. We have gone on the
streets. We've done many things. Now,
I'm not saying that they are wrong.
That's not what I'm saying.
What I am saying
I don't feel that we have contributed to
the healing of the nation.
We've contributed to the awareness
and this and the and and and the
proclamation of our displeasure.
But I think the next step then
the next step
is to now
contributing to the healing of our
nation.
Nehemiah refuses
that life of not contributing to the
healing of the nation. He picks up a
stone and he rebuilds a wall. And I
think that is what God is calling some
of us to do today. Not to fix
everything.
Not to say
Not to rebuild every wall. No, no, no,
no.
But to stop standing in the sidelines
and rebuilding section of the wall that
God has placed in front of you.
Maybe your wall
is refusing to participate in corruption
when everybody else is.
Maybe your wall is becoming an informed
voter
and helping the people around you to
become informed voters.
Maybe your wall is serving your
community. By the way, you know about
voting registration?
Uh
when the exercise closes, you can still
go to the IBC offices and register.
You know that, eh?
Eh that You went You know, most people
think now the the registration exercise
campaign ended, so I I I I'm late. I
can't register. Go
Go to the offices. They have offices in
every county. Go and register. Anyway,
that's not the point.
Eh the point is
eh
probably that may be your wall. Maybe
your wall is serving your community.
Maybe your wall is consistent
involvement in public participation.
Whatever your wall is, pick up a stone
and start building.
Because walls are not built by
spectators.
Walls are not built by conversations.
Walls are built by people who stay go
there to that pile and pick up the stone
and start building. So, pick up a stone
and build a wall.
Now, I want to conclude this message.
And and I find myself thinking about
stand Nehemiah standing before
those broken walls. So, when I made the
visit,
a wall that everybody had seen,
a wall that everybody had talked
a wall that everybody had opinions
about, yet a wall that still remained
broken.
I'm And And maybe this is why this this
this story
speaks to us powerfully today cuz I feel
that's where we are as a as a country.
We live in a world of hashtags, a world
of awareness, a world of opinions and a
world of outrage. A world where
everybody knows what is wrong, but
Nehemiah reminds us
that awareness is not the destination.
It is the beginning.
The challenge before us
is not whether we can identify the
problem. Most of us can do that.
The challenge is whether we are willing
to take the responsibility
for a piece of wall that God has placed
in front of us.
The challenge is whether we are going we
are willing to take the responsibility
of rebuilding a piece of wall that God
has placed in front of us.
So, will we recognize the wall? That's
the question.
Will we respond to the wall?
Will we rebuild the wall?
Because the future
guys, the future is not shaped by people
who merely observe what is broken.
It is shaped by people who are willing
to pick up a stone and start building.
Sadly, for for for us believers
we allow people who are not of God or do
not even have godly values
to pick up stones and start building and
they build monstrosities that oppress
us.
Because we are not willing
to start to pick up a stone and start
building something that will save the
nation.
And perhaps that is God's invitation to
us today. Not to stand in the sidelines.
Not to retreat into silence.
Not to live in perpetual outrage. But to
move beyond the hashtag
and become part of the rebuilding.
Pick up a stone
and build a wall. Tell your neighbor,
pick up a stone
and rebuild a wall.
So, I want us to pray.
Probably you're here.
And you have a burden. As we were
talking about this, God has reminded you
of that burden.
That burden for orphans, that burden for
children, that burden for corrupt
against corruption, that burden for
unfair treatment at the workplace. You
know whatever God has put that wall that
God has put in your face.
You know that one.
And you hear and you're like, "Hey God,
what do I do?"
Or probably you're here and you're like,
"God, I don't even know what is my
burden. Everything confuses me. I'm
angry about this this week, I'm angry
about the other thing this week."
Or probably you're here and you know
you know what you can do. You know what
is a problem.
You know what God has called you to do.
But either you've faced so much pain or
you faced so much opposition that you
don't you're not sure you can move or
you can do anything.
I want to pray for you if that is you.
Mighty Father,
I come before you today, Lord. Lord,
here we are. You've moved our hearts to
things
that
that affect our society.
You've you've you've highlighted to us
even the wall that is before us.
Some of us, Lord, have not been able
even to see it. Lord, we pray open our
eyes.
Open our eyes to clearly see the wall
you've placed in front of us.
Open our eyes to see the brokenness,
Lord, that you're calling us to to to
impact or do something about.
Lord, I pray that even before we we we
run into action, that we first come to
you and pray and ask you for direction.
Because we know, Lord, with your
direction, whatever solution we come up
with, Lord,
will be a solution, Lord, that is
healing.
A solution that does not divide.
A solution that does not kill, but a
solution that brings life.
Lord, we pray for courage. Courage to
overcome the pain we have faced. Courage
to overcome the frustration we've faced.
Courage, oh God, to step out, oh Lord,
and follow you and obey you in this
situation you've called us to be of
impact to. Lord, I pray for resources. I
pray for wisdom. I pray for
partnerships. I pray for courage. I pray
for protection, Lord. And to your
servants, Lord, when they step out in
boldness, Lord,
to do what you've called them to do, to
bring healing to the nation.
And to the nations around us.
Lord, we pray
that you enable us. In Jesus' mighty
name we pray and believe. Amen.
Amen. Now, if you're here and you've not
given your life to Jesus as your Lord
and savior, this is your chance to give
your life to Jesus as your Lord and
savior. Why? Because I can tell you
this.
Your
you Your life and destiny will have more
meaning when you have Jesus on your side
than when you have him away from you.
The the the impact you will have will be
godly impact. Impact that brings
healing.
And so so if you're here and you've not
given your life to Jesus, the first step
is to give your life to Jesus. Or
probably you're here and you're saved
before.
But life has happened and things have
happened and slowly either or or quickly
you have drifted away from salvation.
And you're here and you want to say, "I
want to rededicate my life to Jesus." If
that is you, lift up your hand and we'll
pray for you as well.
Lift up your hand and we'll pray for you
as well.
This is your chance. Do not be afraid.
This chance is for you. This opportunity
is for you.
And I know there's somebody who's
supposed to get saved this weekend. I'm
not sure whether it was first service or
my second service, but if it is you,
please lift up your hand and we'll pray
with you.
Thank you for that hand. Give it up for
our brother over there. Thank you for
that hand.
Thank you for that hand. Anyone else?
Anyone else?
If that is you, if you want to
rededicate, thank you for that hand.
Thank you for that hand. Give it up for
our brother over there.
Uh anyone else? You know
the In fact, you probably that I know
your heart is beating.
I think there's a lady somewhere. If
your heart your heart is beating, you
know this is you. God has been
convicting you and asking you questions
over the last few months, and you know
it is you. Just lift your hand up and
we'll pray with you.
And you probably God is calling you just
to rededicate your life or to give your
life fully to him.
That is you, just lift up your hand.
Do not be afraid. Don't worry what thing
people will think. This is your choice.
And it is your salvation.
So,
uh I want us to So, you guys you can
repeat this prayer after me. Even all of
us, let us support
our two brothers here
uh for giving for giving their life to
Jesus. And so that So, we pray we we
repeat this prayer with them in support
of them. So,
say Lord Jesus,
I come before you today.
Thank you, Lord,
for dying on the cross for my sins.
I ask you forgive me all my sins.
Receive you as my Lord and Savior.
Come into my heart, Lord Jesus,
and make me who you want me to be.
Uh remove me from my past
and create a new future for me.
Now, now lift your index finger like
this and say,
"Devil,
you and I are finished.
I belong to Jesus.
Everything that I did for you is now
done.
I now serve the mighty King Jesus.
And I belong to Jesus.
In Jesus' name,
amen.
Amen. Amen. Amen.
Ah.
Love it. Anyway, um
what was I saying? Oh, yes. Let me pray
for them.
Almighty Father,
uh we thank you, Lord, for our two
brothers who've given their lives to
you. Lord, may this be the turn around
of their lives. Lord, I pray that you
give them community, friends who will
take them to you. Uh who will bring in
prayer and even in counsel that will
consistently be bring them back to you,
Lord. Lord, I pray that any addiction,
any power of evil that has been
following them over time, Lord, we break
it in the mighty name of Jesus. We
decree that their faith shall stand. We
decree that their lives shall never be
the same. We decree in the mighty name
of Jesus that their families shall be
shall be changed because of their
salvation. Lord, from today, I ask you,
Lord, may you fill them, Lord, with the
Holy Spirit. Walk with them, oh Holy
Spirit. Fill them again and empower
them. May they walk their in the
direction you've called them to, and may
they live a life of destiny. And Lord,
may they at the end of their lives may
they look at the impact
they have caused over
for your kingdom and be happy. In Jesus'
mighty name we pray and believe. Amen.
Amen. Amen. Amen. And it's that time we
love, it's time to
It's time to give. It's time to give. We
can them 400 22
uh is a paybill number. The account name
is 1130128
hash. You have to put the hash or else
this I tend to hash. And then whatever
you're giving, if you're giving tithe,
if you're giving offering, if you're
supporting someone,
uh like you can write their name. If you
want to give to arms, whatever it is you
want to give, just write it down over
there and then our accountants will be
like this money was put as this and
we'll be able to do that with it. So,
You only saw
Yes, why do I give? Why do I give? Most
of the time when I come on a on a do
giving, I share why I'm giving and I
have a I usually have a reason every
day.
Uh and and for me my reason for giving
is a spread of the gospel.
Let me tell you.
I My life has really changed because of
being in church.
I was not once in the people who know me
before salvation. I don't know I know
this church nobody knows me before
salvation. They they are not here. They
did not come today.
Yes, no they they have come a few times.
Hey, they they knew me as a drunk, as a
what, as many things.
But, because of church, I've been able
to find Jesus, find purpose, find a
family, find a spouse, find many things.
And I'm like, if it was not for church,
what would happen? So, for me I give so
that because I know at least for this
church, Mavuno Church, we're
consistently planting churches. So,
because we'll we'll help plant another
church and create another space where
someone like me can find Jesus and their
life can turn around. That is why I
give.
Yes, and I hope you have given.
It is the beginning of the month one of
the things I challenge people is go
home, budget,
decide what you're going to give to God,
and then give it. So,
so that you you don't give out of
compulsion, out of you know you you
you see you and out of meaning you you
you and God sit and you're like, this is
what I'm giving you this month. And now
you give that. So.
Awesome. Let me bless you all.
May God bless you. May God shine his
face towards you. May God give you
courage and wisdom to not only recognize
the world that is placed before you,
but also to give you the wisdom on what
to do and the courage to actually do it.
May God raise people around you to to to
help achieve what God has put in your
heart. But also, may God give you peace.
May God give you joy. May God provide
for you and cover and protect you. In
Jesus' mighty name we pray and believe.
Amen. Amen.